A Guide to the Theodosius G. Dobzhansky papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA159
Rockefeller Archive Center
Theodosius G. Dobzhansky papers, Rockefeller University Faculty
undated
Rockefeller Archive Center
Bronk, Detlev W. (Detlev Wulf), 1897-1975
Rockefeller University
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Dobzhansky, Theodosius Grigorievich
FA159
0.44 Cubic Feet 1 box
1 box (5 inches)
Biographical/Historical note
Theodosius Dobzhansky, 1900-1975, was "a major influence on current thought and research on genetic, evolutionary theory and human evolution". A world renowned geneticist, famous for his research, writing and lecturing about evolution and genetics and their relationship to modern man. He pioneered the use of fruit flies which proved to be excellent research animals.
Biographical note
1900 Born January 25 in Nemirov, Russia
1921 Graduate and Diplomate University of Kiev
1921-1924 Assistant in Zoology Polytechnic Institute, Kiev
1924-1927 Lecturer and Assistant Professor in genetics University of Leningrad
1927-1929 General Education Board Fellow at Columbia University with Thomas Hunt Morgan
1929-1936 Assistant Professor Genetics California Institute of Technology (with T.H. Morgan)
1936-1940 Professor Genetics California Institute of Technology
1940-1958 Professor of Zoology Columbia University
1958-1962 da Costa Professor of Zoology Columbia University
1962-1970 Professor Rockefeller Institute and Rockefeller University
1970-1975 Professor Emeritus Rockefeller University
1971-1975 Adjunct Professor Genetics University of California, Davis
1975 Died December 18 Davis, California
Awards
1946 Daniel Giraud Elliot Medal NAS
1958 Kimber Award and Medal NAS
1959 Darwin Medal Academia Leopoldina
1963 Anisfield-Wolf Book Award
1963 Pierre Lecomte du Nouy Award
1964 Rational Medal of Science
1966 Addison Emery Verrill Medal, Yale University
1969 Gold Medal for Distinguished Achievement of Science, American Museum of Natural History
1973 Benjamin Franklin Medal, Franklin Institute, Philadelphia
Honorary degrees
1943 University of Sao Paulo
1945 Wooster College, Ohio
1958 University of Münster
1958 University of Montreal
1959 University of Chicago
1960 University of Sydney
1964 Columbia University, NY
1964 University of Oxford
1965 University of Louvain
1965 Clarksin College of Technology
1966 Kalamazoo College
1966 University of Michigan
1967 Syracuse University
1968 University of Padua
1968 University of California Berkeley
1968 Northwestern University
1970 Wittenberg University
1970 St. Mary's College
1970 St. Vladimir Theological Academy, NY
1975 Mazatlan University, Mexico
1975 Sorbonne, Paris
Membership: Genetics Society of America (president 1941), American Society of Naturalists (president 1950), Society for the Study of Evolution (president 1951), American Society of Zoologists (president 1963), American Teilhard de Chardin Association (president 1969), Behavior Genetics Association (president 1973), National Academy of Sciences, American Philosophical Association, American Academy of Arts and Sciences, Genetics Society of Japan (honorary), Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences (foreign member), Royal Danish Academy of Sciences (foreign member), Brazilian Academy of Sciences (foreign member), Academia Nazionale dei Lincei (foreign member), Royal Society of London (foreign member).
Scope and Contents note
This group of papers consists mainly of correspondence.
List of publications enclosed with papers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The papers of Theodosius Dobzhansky were deposited with the Rockefeller University Archives on June 1980 by Office of Faculty and Student Records.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 D656
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research.
Bronk, Detlev W. (Detlev Wulf), 1897-1975; Rockefeller University; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Dobzhansky, Theodosius Grigorievich
- Correspondence and miscellaneous, 1956-1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence with D.W. Bronk, D. Whitaker and F. Seitz
  - Employment record at Rockefeller University
  - Photographs: portraits and laboratory photos
  - Report to colleagues on collecting trip to Venezuela, Trinidad and British Guiana, 1963
  - Letter to Dr. Bronk complaining about Dr. Dobzhansky written by Carleton S. Coon, 1963
  - Book review of translation by I.M. Lerner of book by Z.A. Medvedev "The rise and fall of T.D. Lysenko", 1963; Typescript copy
- Correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Program of lectures at RU, 1970 October 6 1970 October 13 1970 October 20 1970 October 27 1970 November 3 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- News clippings (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Biographical Memoir Fellow of Royal Society 23, 59-89, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Memoir American Philosophical Society Yearbook 49-53, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Announcement of Memorial Meeting at Columbia, 1976 April 9-10 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Collected reprints (scattered holdings) (Box 1, Folder 2)